Hey, what's up guys? My name is Acherno,
and welcome back to my C++ series. Last
time we talked about virtual functions,
and today we're going to be talking
about a specific type of virtual
function, something called a pure
virtual function. A pure virtual
function in C++ is essentially the same
as an abstract method or an interface in
other languages such as Java or C#.
Basically, a pure virtual function
allows us to define a function in a base
class that does not have an
implementation, and then force
subclasses to actually implement that
function. If we take a look at our
example from the previous video, which
was about virtual functions, you can see
that we had a virtual get name function
inside the entity class, and then we had
an override for that function inside our
player class. By having this get name
function inside our base class with an
actual body means that overriding it in
a subclass such as player is entirely
optional. If we didn't override it, then
we could still call player.getname.
However, it would of course return the
entity string. However, in some cases,
it doesn't make sense for us to provide
this default implementation. We actually
might want to force the subclass to
actually provide its own definition for
a certain function. In object-oriented
programming, it's actually quite common
for us to create a class that consists
only of unimplemented methods, and then
force a subclass to actually implement
them. This is something that's often
referred to as an interface. So, an
interface being a class that only
consists of unimplemented methods and
acting as a template of sorts. And since
this interface class doesn't actually
contain method implementations, it's not
actually possible for us to instantiate
that class. Let's see if we can make
this get name function inside entity a
pure virtual function. To do that, I'm
just going to get rid of the body, and
instead of the body, just write equals
zero. Keep in mind that it still has to
be defined as virtual, but the equal
zero is essentially making it a pure
virtual function, meaning that it has to
be implemented in a subclass if you want
to be able to instantiate that class.
So, by doing this, a few things have
actually happened. First of all, if you
look at main, you can see that we now no
longer have the ability to actually
instantiate that entity class. We must
give it some kind of subclass that
actually has that function implemented.
So, in this case, player, for example.
And of course, we need to provide some
kind of string as well. You can see the
player works fine. However, that's only
because we've actually implemented that
get name function. If I decide to
comment out that implementation, you can
see that we can't instantiate player
either. So, essentially, you can only
instantiate the class if it actually has
all of those pure virtual functions
implemented. Or classes further up in
the hierarchy, so for example, if player
were to be a subclass of another class
which did implement that get name
function, that would also be fine. But
the idea is that get name, that pure
virtual function, has to actually be
implemented in order for us to be able
to create an instance of this class. All
right, let's take a look at a better
example. I'm going to undo everything
that we had done here. All right, that
looks pretty good. Suppose that we
wanted to write a function that would
print the class name of every class that
we had here. So, what I'll do is I'll
type void print. As my parameter, I'm
going to want to take in some kind of
class type that we'll call obj, for
example. And then, what I'm going to
want to do is actually print the class's
name. So, maybe we have something like
obj.getclassname.
So, what I actually need here is a type
that guarantees that we actually have a
get class name function. We need a type
that provides that get class name
function. And that's exactly what an
interface is. Let's go ahead and call
this type printable, and we'll set it
up. So, at the very top here, I'll make
a new class called printable, and the
only thing this is going to have, I'm
going to make it public virtual string
function that returns a string here,
getclassname, and it's going to be pure
virtual. So, I'm going to set it equal
to zero. Then, I'm going to make entity
implement that interface.
Note that player is already an entity,
so we don't have to implement printable.
However, if it wasn't for whatever
reason, we could just add a comma and
then implement an interface like so.
Keep in mind that I keep calling this an
interface, but of course, it is just a
class. The reason I've given it the name
interface here is because all it has is
that pure virtual function and that is
it. Other languages actually do have an
interface keyword instead of class, but
C++ does not. Interfaces are just
classes in C++. So now everything has to
have this get class name function. If it
does not, you can't actually instantiate
it. Let's go ahead and add a get class
name function for entity. Now, if we
were to do what we did here inside
player, I'll just write STD string get
class name, return entity, then we
actually have a few issues. First of
all, our problem of not being able to
instantiate entity is solved, of course,
because we have provided that function.
However, you'll notice that we haven't
provided one for player. So if I go down
to print, let's make this a pointer, and
actually call print with both player and
entity, we'll get rid of print names so
we're not confused here. Here, five. Of
course, you can see that we get entity
printing twice because we haven't
actually provided a definition in
player. However, if we do, so if I just
try and copy this get class name, which
of course is an override, let's not
forget that. If I pop that down here and
rename this to player, I can hit F5 here
to run my code, and you can see that I
now get the appropriate class name
printing. And all of that's coming from
that one print function that takes in a
printable object. It doesn't really care
what class it is. We could create a
completely different class here, such as
A, that is a printable class, meaning
that it has to have that function. If it
does not have that get class name
function, then you won't be able to
instantiate
an instance of this class. If we do
something like this, I've created a
brand new class, I've made it printable,
meaning that I have implemented this
function. I can now call print like
this. Of course, don't write this code
exactly cuz it's a memory leak, but for
testing, it's fine. If I do something
like this, you can see that we now get
that A class printing here. And because
it is a printable, it is guaranteed to
have that get class name function.
That's how this whole thing works,
because it knows that anything that is
printable has a get class name function
for this to actually call. If you do not
implement that function, then you will
not be able to instantiate the class.
So, that's it. That is what an interface
is in C++. That's what a pure virtual
function is in C++. Very, very useful
stuff. The number one reason it's really
used is for situations like this, where
you want to be able to guarantee that a
class has a certain function, so that
you can pass it to a fairly generic
method that will just call that function
or do whatever it needs to do. Hope you
guys enjoyed this video. As always, you
can leave any questions or comments you
have in the comment section below. I try
to reply to as many comments as I can,
and I will see you guys next time.
Goodbye.